A Guide to the Nelson W. Aldrich papers FA068
Rockefeller Archive Center
Nelson W. Aldrich papers
1777-1930, bulk 1879-1915
1879-1915
Rockefeller Archive Center
Aldrich, Nelson W. (Nelson Wilmarth)
United States. Congress. Senate
United States. National Monetary Commission
FA068
1.26 Cubic Feet 63 microfilm reels
Arrangement note
The Nelson W. Aldrich papers are arranged in 10 series:
Series 1 - Diaries and Notebooks
Series 2 - General Correspondence
Series 3 - Tariff
Series 4 - National Monetary Commission
Series 5 - Biographer's Papers
Series 6 - Financial Papers
Series 7 - Speech File
Series 8 - Serials
Series 9 - Printed Matter
Series 10 - Miscellany
Biographical/Historical note
1841, November 6: Born in Foster, Rhode Island
1862: Served with 10th Rhode Island Volunteers
1865: Became junior partner in Rhode Island wholesale grocery firm
1866: Married Abby Chapman
1869-1875: Member of Providence Common Council; president, 1872-1873
1875-1877: Member of State House of Representatives; Speaker of the House, 1876-1877
1876: Delegate to Republican National Convention
1879-1881: Member of U.S. House of Representatives
1881-1911: Member of U.S. Senate
1908-1912: Chairman of National Monetary Commission
1915, April 16: Died in New York, New York
Scope and Contents note
The papers of Nelson W. Aldrich (1841-1915), statesman, financier, and businessman, span the years 1777 to 1930, with the bulk of the material concentrated in the years 1879 to 1915. The collection is composed primarily of correspondence, printed matter, and material relating to tariff legislation and the National Monetary Commission, supplemented by diaries, notebooks, speeches, research notes, serials, financial papers, and miscellaneous items.
The collection focuses on Aldrich's 30 years of service as a U.S. Senator from Rhode Island, 1881 to 1911. During this lengthy career, Aldrich rose from the relatively obscure position of junior Senator from a small state to become one of the most influential members of the Senate by the close of the nineteenth century. His elevation to the chairmanship of the powerful Senate Finance Committee in 1899 underscored his national prominence, a fact recognized by successive Presidents until his voluntary retirement in 1911. Aldrich's primary concern as a senator centered on national economic and fiscal policy, particularly tariff and monetary policy. By personal business experience, ideological considerations, and the realities of Rhode Island politics, Aldrich normally exerted his influence on behalf of the protective tariff rates and conservative monetary policies favored by powerful northeastern business interests.
The Aldrich papers reflect the Senator's deep involvement with national economic policy. Tariff legislation is a recurring theme throughout the correspondence series, particularly during the years of major tariff revision in 1890, 1897, and 1909. The correspondence, mainly incoming mail from businessmen representing a wide range of economic interests, reveals the depth of feeling generated by the prospect of tariff revision and the importance of the issue during these years. The letters also provide an insight into American business practices and the economic views of a large segment of the American business community during this era of rapid industrial expansion. Aldrich's personal attention to the details of rate revision is clearly revealed in the tariff file, while his speeches help document his general attitude toward tariff duties as a source of protection for American industry from foreign competition.
Aldrich gave considerable attention during his last years in office to the problems of U.S. monetary policy. Following the Panic of 1907, with its accompanying rash of bank failures, he cosponsored the Aldrich-Vreeland Act of 1908, providing for the establishment of a National Monetary Commission to study banking and currency operations at home and abroad and to suggest changes in American practices.
The National Monetary Commission's correspondence for the years 1908-1912 thoroughly documents its activities and Aldrich's role as chairman. Much of the Commission's correspondence was with bankers, public officials, financial experts, and academicians employed to prepare special studies, translate documents, and collect statistics on financial operations and monetary systems in foreign nations as well as in the United States. Aldrich and other members of the Commission visited England, France, and Germany to consult with experts and collect data, and specialists representing the Commission made similar visits to other nations and reported their findings. Hearings were held in selected American cities to solicit opinions from bankers and other interested parties, while numerous individuals sent unsolicited opinions and plans directly to the Commission. Most of the letters were sent and received by Abram Piatt Andrew, special assistant to the Commission, Arthur B. Shelton, secretary to the Commission, and staff members Charles E. Alden, J. Williar Sheetz, and William A. Slade.
Aldrich's personal views are reflected in occasional correspondence, speeches delivered to promote monetary reform, and in the final report of the Commission--soon labeled the "Aldrich Plan." The Commission's correspondence is also a rich source of information for students of American financial institutions of the early twentieth century and expounds the views of a small but influential segment of the financial community at this time. The National Monetary Commission file contains most of its publications as well as a sampling of the collected data and related material.
Soon after the death of Senator Henry B. Anthony in 1884, Aldrich assumed Anthony's former position as the most powerful figure in Rhode Island politics. Letters from numerous state political figures, particularly Henry B. Gardner and Charles R. Brayton, kept the busy Senator abreast of local affairs and at the same time reveal his influence in state political circles. The numerous requests for favors, advice, and patronage further attest to his influence.
Aldrich's personal affairs and family relations form a relatively small portion of the collection. A short series of letters written to his future wife in 1865-1866 offers a glimpse into his personal relations and plans at this time. Another small group of letters written to Mrs. Aldrich during his first trip abroad in 1872-1873 adds to our knowledge of his family relations and reveals his initial impressions of European society and culture. Scattered letters in the correspondence series and the financial papers allow a brief insight into his extensive financial ventures, particularly his investments in the rubber industry.
Aldrich's principal correspondents include William B. Allison, Henry B. Anthony, Jonathan Bourne, Jr., Charles R. Brayton, Jonathan Chace, William E. Chandler, Charles A. Conant, Henry P. Davison, Eugene Hale, Philander C. Knox, Charles Warren Lippitt, Stephen B. Luce, Orville H. Platt, Theodore Roosevelt, William Howard Taft, Henry M. Teller, Paul M. Warburg, and George Peabody Wetmore.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The Rockefeller Archive Center purchased a microfilm copy of a large portion of the Nelson W. Aldrich papers, the originals of which are in the custody of the Manuscript Division of the Library of Congress.
The papers of Nelson Wilmarth Aldrich were presented to the Library of Congress in four installments. The first installment was received in 1944 from Aldrich's children, Winthrop W. Aldrich and Abby Aldrich Rockefeller; and Mr. John D. Rockefeller, Jr., made two additions to the collection in 1955 and 1956 from the papers of his late wife, Abby Aldrich Rockefeller. The last installment was presented to the Library in 1970 by the Seminary of Our Lady of Providence, Rhode Island.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Existence and Location of Originals
The original records are held by the Manuscript Division of the Library of Congress and are not available at the RAC. User copies of the microfilm are available for scholarly access.
Economics; Epidemics; Taxation -- Law and legislation -- United States; Economic policy; United States. Congress. Senate -- History -- 20th century; United States. Congress. Senate -- History -- 19th century
- Diaries and Notebooks, 1863-1927, n.d.; 01
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains diaries and social engagement books of Abby C. Aldrich, bound and unbound shorthand letters and notes of Nelson W. Aldrich, a Civil War company roll book, a fraternal lodge address book, minutes of the Senate Finance Committee for Dec. 1863 to June 1864, and a journal relating to the Hepburn Act of 1906.
  - Diaries and Notebooks (Reel 1)
    Related Materials
    Container 1, available from the Manuscripts Division, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. 20540
    Scope and Contents
    Abby C. Aldrich diaries (2), Jan. 1904 and Jan.-May 1912 Abby C. Aldrich engagement books (5), 1905-10 Hepburn Act journal, no author, 1927 Civil War roll book, 1863 Fraternal lodge address book, no date Senate Finance Committee minutes, Dec. 1863-June 1864 Bound shorthand letters, ca. Dec. 1882-Jan. 1884 Bound shorthand notes, no date Unbound shorthand letters, ca. 1882-1909 and undated
- General Correspondence, 1777-1915, n.d.; 02
  Arrangement note
  This series is arranged chronologically by day.
  This series contains letters received and occasional letters sent by Nelson W. Aldrich, and letters sent and received by staff members of the National Monetary Commission.
  - 1777, 1846-November 1879 (Reel 2)
    Container 2, available from the Manuscripts Division, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. 20540
  - December 1879 - January 1881 (Reel 3)
    Containers 3-4, available from the Manuscripts Division, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. 20540
  - February-December 1881 and [1881] (Reel 4)
    Container 5 available from the Manuscripts Division, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. 20540
  - January-March 1882 (Reel 5)
    Container 6 available from the Manuscripts Division, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. 20540
  - April-June 1882 (Reel 6)
    Container 7 available from the Manuscripts Division, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. 20540
  - April-June 1882 - December 15, 1882-January 19, 1883 (Reel 7)
    Container 7-9 available from the Manuscripts Division, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. 20540
  - December 15, 1882-January 19, 1883 - March-August 1883 (Reel 8)
    Containers 9-11, available from the Manuscripts Division, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. 20540
  - March-August 1883 - September 1-December 26, 1883 (Reel 9)
    Containers 11-12, available from the Manuscripts Division, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. 20540
  - September 1-December 26, 1883 - December 27, 1883-February 29, 1884 (Reel 10)
    Containers 12-13, available from the Manuscripts Division, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. 20540
  - March 1-April 25, 1884 - April 26-June 30, 1884 (Reel 11)
    Containers 14-15, available from the Manuscripts Division, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. 20540
  - April 26-June 30, 1884 - July-October 1884 (Reel 12)
    Containers 15-16, available from the Manuscripts Division, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. 20540
  - November 1, 1884-January 21, 1885 - January 22-February 28, 1885 (Reel 13)
    Containers 17-18, available from the Manuscripts Division, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. 20540
  - January 22-February 28, 1885 - March-July 1885 (Reel 14)
    Containers 18-19, available from the Manuscripts Division, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. 20540
  - March-July 1885 - January-February 1886 (Reel 15)
    Containers 19-21, available from the Manuscripts Division, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. 20540
  - January-February 1886 - March-April 1886 (Reel 16)
    Containers 21-22, available from the Manuscripts Division, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. 20540
  - March-April 1886 - May-June 1886 (Reel 17)
    Containers 22-23, available from the Manuscripts Division, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. 20540
  - May-June 1886 - 1887-1888 (Reel 18)
    Containers 23-25, available from the Manuscripts Division, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. 20540
  - 1887-1888 - May-September 1889 (Reel 19)
    Containers 25-27, available from the Manuscripts Division, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. 20540
  - May-September 1889 - October 1889-December 1890 and [1890] (Reel 20)
    Containers 27-28, available from the Manuscripts Division, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. 20540
  - January 1891-July 1892 - August 1892-June 1897 (Reel 21)
    Containers 29-30, available from the Manuscripts Division, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. 20540
  - July 1897-May 1899 (Reel 22)
    Container 31, available from the Manuscripts Division, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. 20540
  - June 1899-September 1900 - May 1902-June 1903 (Reel 23)
    Containers 32-34, available from the Manuscripts Division, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. 20540
  - July 1903-September 1905 - October 1905-December 1906 and [1906] (Reel 24)
    Containers 35-36, available from the Manuscripts Division, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. 20540
  - January 1907-January 1908 (Reel 25)
    Container 37, available from the Manuscripts Division, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. 20540
  - February-April 1908 (Reel 26)
    Container 38, available from the Manuscripts Division, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. 20540
  - May-August 1908 (Reel 27)
    Container 39, available from the Manuscripts Division, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. 20540
  - September-December 1908 and [1908] (Reel 28)
    Container 40, available from the Manuscripts Division, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. 20540
  - January 1-February 8, 1909 (Reel 29)
    Container 41, available from the Manuscripts Division, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. 20540
  - February 9-March 13, 1909 - March 14-31, 1909 (Reel 30)
    Containers 42-43, available from the Manuscripts Division, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. 20540
  - April 1-19, 1909 (Reel 31)
    Container 44, available from the Manuscripts Division, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. 20540
  - April 20-May 12, 1909 (Reel 32)
    Container 45, available from the Manuscripts Division, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. 20540
  - May 13-June 11, 1909 (Reel 33)
    Container 46, available from the Manuscripts Division, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. 20540
  - June 12-July 10, 1909 (Reel 34)
    Container 47, available from the Manuscripts Division, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. 20540
  - July 11-August 8, 1909 (Reel 35)
    Container 48, available from the Manuscripts Division, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. 20540
  - August 9-September 22, 1909 (Reel 36)
    Container 49, available from the Manuscripts Division, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. 20540
  - September 23-November 15, 1909 (Reel 37)
    Container 50, available from the Manuscripts Division, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. 20540
  - November 16-December 23, 1909 (Reel 38)
    Container 51, available from the Manuscripts Division, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. 20540
  - December 24, 1909-January 31, 1910 (Reel 39)
    Container 52, available from the Manuscripts Division, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. 20540
  - February 1-March 17, 1910 (Reel 40)
    Container 53, available from the Manuscripts Division, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. 20540
  - March 18-April 30, 1910 (Reel 41)
    Container 54, available from the Manuscripts Division, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. 20540
  - May-June 1910 - July-September 1910 (Reel 42)
    Containers 55-56, available from the Manuscripts Division, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. 20540
  - October 1-December 15, 1910 (Reel 43)
    Container 57, available from the Manuscripts Division, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. 20540
  - December 16, 1910-February 24, 1911 (Reel 44)
    Container 58, available from the Manuscripts Division, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. 20540
  - February 25-May 31, 1911 - June-September 1911 (Reel 45)
    Containers 59-60, available from the Manuscripts Division, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. 20540
  - October 1-December 13, 1911 (Reel 46)
    Container 61, available from the Manuscripts Division, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. 20540
  - December 14, 1911-April 30, 1912 - May 1912-February 1914 (Reel 47)
    Containers 62-63, available from the Manuscripts Division, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. 20540
  - March-December 1914 and [1914] - January-June 1915 and Undated (Reel 48)
    Containers 64-65, available from the Manuscripts Division, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. 20540
- Tariff, ca. 1880-1915; 03
  This series is grouped by type of material where possible but otherwise unarranged.
  This series contains bills, amendments, schedules, petitions, resolutions, reports, statements, and miscellaneous items relating to tariff rates and tariff legislation.
  - Bills, Amendments, Schedules (Reel 49)
    Containers 66-70, available from the Manuscripts Division, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. 20540
  - Bills, Amendments, Schedules (Reel 50)
  - Bills, Amendments, Schedules (Reel 51)
  - Bills, Amendments, Schedules (Reel 52)
  - Miscellaneous Schedules, Petitions, Statements, Statistics, Reports, Memoranda, Resolutions, and Fragments Relating to the Tariff (Reel 53)
    Containers 71-74, available from the Manuscripts Division, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. 20540
  - Miscellaneous Schedules, Petitions, Statements, Statistics, Reports, Memoranda, Resolutions, and Fragments Relating to the Tariff (Reel 54)
- National Monetary Commission, 1908-1912; 04
  This series is unarranged.
  This series contains publications of the National Monetary Commission and miscellaneous draft reports, proceedings, statements, statistics, and papers relating to the National Monetary Commission.
  Related Archival Materials note
  This series is not available at the Rockefeller Archive Center. It has been microfilmed and may be available to researchers through a local public or university library, or through the Library of Congress's Manuscripts Division.
- Biographer's Papers, ca. 1860-1930, n.d.; 05
  This series is arranged by type of material and chronologically therein.
  This series contains research notes collected by Jeannette P. Nichols and Nathaniel W. Stephenson for the latter's biography, "Nelson W. Aldrich, a Leader in American Politics" (1930), supplemented by one folder of related correspondence and a few miscellaneous items.
  - Biographer's Papers (Reel 58)
    Container 85, available from the Manuscripts Division, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. 20540
    Correspondence, 1924-30 and undated General outline Interviews, memoranda, miscellaneous Notes, ca. 1860-86
  - Notes, 1887-1893 - Notes, 1884-1901 (Reel 59)
    Containers 86-87, available from the Manuscripts Division, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. 20540
  - Notes, 1884-1901 - Notes, 1902-1905 (Reel 60)
    Containers 87-89, available from the Manuscripts Division, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. 20540
  - Notes, 1906-1915 (Reel 60)
    Containers 90-91, available from the Manuscripts Division, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. 20540
- Financial Papers, ca. 1880-1915; 06
  This series contains checkbooks, checks, statements, bills, receipts, vouchers, occasional correspondence, and miscellaneous items relating to both Nelson W. Aldrich's personal financial affairs and the financial transactions of the National Monetary Commission.
  - Financial papers (Reel 61)
- Speech File, 1881-1913, n.d.; 07
  This series is arranged chronologically and by type of material.
  This series contains holograph, typed, and printed speeches by Nelson W. Aldrich, including drafts and related research material.
  - 1881-1990 - 1891-November 1909 (Reel 62)
    Containers 101-102, available from the Manuscripts Division, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. 20540
  - November 1909-October 1911 - November 1911-October 1913; Notes for Tariff Speeches (Reel 63)
    Containers 103-104, available from the Manuscripts Division, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. 20540
  - November 1911-October 1913; Notes for Tarrif Speeches; Notes for Monetary Speeches; Undated and Fragments (Reel 64)
    Containers 104-106, available from the Manuscripts Division, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. 20540
- Serials, ca. 1885-1915; 08
  This series contains scattered issues of five serial publications, grouped by title and arranged chronologically therein, and miscellaneous journals, unarranged.
- Printed Matter, ca. 1880-1915; 09
  This series is grouped by type of material but is otherwise unarranged.
  This series contains government documents and bound and unbound printed matter.
- Miscellany, ca. 1862-1915; 10
  This series is grouped by type of material.
  This series contains bound facsimile letters, biographical information, material relating to Aldrich's rubber investments, speeches, articles, memoranda, proceedings, briefs, cases, contracts, reports, requests for supplies, cards, tickets, three scrapbooks of clippings relating primarily to tariff and banking matters, acknowledgments, invitations, loose clippings, photographs, and miscellaneous items.
  Reels 70-73 of this series are not available at the Rockefeller Archive Center. Researchers should consult a local public or university library for this portion of the microfilm edition, or the Library of Congress's Manuscripts Division.
  - Miscellany (Reel 68)
    Containers 130-131, available from the Manuscripts Division, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. 20540
    Briefs; cases
  - Miscellany (Reel 69)
    Containers 131-133, available from the Manuscripts Division, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. 20540
    Speeches and articles, 1891-1915 and undated Memoranda Proceedings Briefs; cases Contracts Reports Requests for supplies Cards; tickets Scrapbook of clippings, 1884-1886, re tarriff (mainly)